WordPress powers over 40% of the internet today.
And while WordPress core is quite secure by now,
if you've ever done anything on WordPress like I did,
you know that you need WordPress plugins
for even small things.
And those plugins, they are not that secure,
but the problem was not finding bugs for them in my past,
the problem was monetizing them well.
But it has changed now, and in this video,
I will show you both how to start
auditing WordPress plugins and how to monetize them
even if the plugin itself
does not have a bug bounty program.
Enjoy.
This video is sponsored by WordFence,
but I will tell you more about it later.
So the first thing that you need for hacking WordPress
is the WordPress instance.
For this, I recommend you to use Docker
and I actually use a Docker Compose file
created by Justin from
the Critical Thinking Bug Bounty Podcast.
You just save this file locally, the Docker Compose YAML,
and then you run Docker Compose app
and it does everything for you.
And your instance is ready in,
it can take even a few minutes
if you don't have the resources downloaded.
And then you can access the local instance
on localhost port 1337.
You just have to go through the usual installation steps,
doesn't matter things that you put in here
because it's only for you anyway.
And then you log in, you have your instance of WordPress.
Then we are interested in WordPress plugins.
So we'll just go to the plugins part
and install, click add new plugin and install a plugin.
I have a prepared one for the presentation.
Is this one just click install?
Then you possibly have to click activate
or something like this.
And then the plugin is installed.
And always as with every website
or every target that I test,
the first thing is to just start using the thing.
So in this case, I just need to use this shortcode
on a page that will,
so I can just see how normally the requests are sent.
I can just paste it somewhere here, click update.
And then when I see this page, I must be unauthenticated.
So I will open it in the incognito window.
Then I will see the feedback part
and I can also submit any response.
I can submit any response.
And now I finally have some requests in Burb
with my response.
It's this one.
Here's my response.
Here's everything.
And when doing the, when editing the source code,
one of the first things I do,
the big thing is I have a request here.
And now I want to find the part of the source code
that's responsible for this response.
And usually the best,
your best bet to do this in pretty much any technology
is to just look by using the endpoint name.
In this case, it's responses
because we can also see this endpoint has the one number.
It's probably the parameter, it's probably the form ID.
And if you install the Docker the way I showed you,
it creates the VPWP content directory
and then the plugins are downloaded here.
So you don't even have to download them manually
to your computer.
They are just synchronized in the folder outside Docker.
And this is the plugin that I'm interested in.
So I will mark find in folder.
And now I'm only finding stuff inside this folder.
I also want to limit this to PHP files.
So I will do this and it gives us a few responses.
Now, the part you are looking for now
in WordPress is register rest route
because this plugin created sort of a new endpoint
in WordPress.
And this is one of the ways
that WordPress plugins use to do this.
I will also show you another way to achieve this later.
And the syntax of this is basically,
here's the base path,
which in this case is just a string,
possibly it can be a constant or a variable or something.
Then you have the endpoint name,
which does match the endpoint I am looking for
because I'm looking for this and it looks correctly.
And then there are another arguments.
Among others, there is an argument called methods.
And we can see that this particular piece
refers to a get method.
But the request I am looking for is actually a post,
which means this is not the part that I'm looking for.
We can also see here a post,
but this one is to responses slash trash.
We can see responses restore also post,
but none of these match my results.
So I will go to another results here.
And I can finally find another rest route
that matches the route I am looking for
and matches the method I am looking for.
So I'm pretty convinced this is the one
that I'm interested in.
Now, the very important thing in the syntax
of this register rest route arguments array
is the permission callback,
because it tells WordPress
which users can perform a specific action.
In this case, this means that it's just a function
that always returns true.
It's quite a strange PHP syntax.
So it means this endpoint is unauthenticated
and it makes a lot of sense,
because as you remember,
I just opened an incognito window to open this.
So definitely it makes sense
because this is a route available to anyone.
And when you're looking for bugs,
you should definitely focus on unauthenticated bugs
because they just have the most impact.
If we take a look at these endpoints,
there's an actual function that does a permission check.
Let's see how this looks like.
We can find this function in the same file,
which calls other function with this argument.
So we have to look for this.
It doesn't really tell us anything.
There is a strange capabilities array.
So this is what we are looking for now.
And finally, after some time,
we get to an array of what roles can perform what actions
or what actions can be performed by what roles.
This is not a standard way.
There's no one specific way to do this,
but generally by looking for the strings like I just did,
I just searched for strings in this code.
I can see that the view results capability,
which is the one I'm interested in,
can be performed by administrator or editor.
Administrator by default in WordPress,
administrator can install plugins
so the administrator can execute code.
So any vulnerability that requires
the administrator capability is out of scope,
at least the server side vulnerability
where the attacker needs this account.
Editor, it's a bit better
because it's not the highest privilege level,
but it's definitely better
if you can exploit the bug unauthenticated
or with the minimal permission level.
So we'll come back to the code we're interested in.
So these endpoints,
they can be executed by administrators or editors.
So I'm not looking for them at the moment
because I want to find an unauthenticated vulnerability.
So I come back to this route.
So now we know what's permission callback,
we know all the other parts,
and then there's the callback argument,
which is actually the function that processes the response.
So I can look for the function with the name,
very often in the same file.
And now I have just found the, oops,
I have just found the function that processed my response.
We won't get into details of this
because it's not that interesting actually,
at least at the moment,
but I have just found the code that processed this request.
And this is for me always the first step
when doing any kind of source code review.
Before I get to another way that plugins can define routes,
and I will also show you an actual bug
in one of the plugins, why to even look for them?
Because as I've told you in the intro,
it used to be quite difficult to monetize them.
Of course, if you have an unauthenticated severe bug,
like server-side bug or an XSS,
you can report the zero-day to many companies
and possibly get paid for them.
But there are a few problems with this.
One problem is that often WordPress is out of scope
and you will just not get paid for these bugs.
The other problem is you need the bug
to be either a server-side bug or an XSS
because it cannot be anything with user interaction.
Even if you have like an account takeover
that only requires one click
or requires the victim to open a website,
that's too much for you to get paid.
And the plugin developers
usually don't host a bug bounty program.
So these plugins, even though they power big part
of the internet, were hard to monetize.
But now there is WordFence bug bounty program,
which covers every single plugin above 50,000 installs.
And I think it's a really, really great opportunity.
WordFence actually sponsors this video
and I'm really happy to collaborate with them
because I genuinely, I genuinely think
it's a good opportunity to make money,
to learn source code review
because these plugins, they are not very secure.
I looked at some of them
and there are really, really a lot of holes in them.
And above 50,000 installs, there are over 800 plugins
which means millions of lines of PHP code
that's potentially vulnerable.
And if you're interested in taking part,
go to bbre.dev slash WF, like WordFence.
So let's come back to another way
that a plugin might define a route.
Let's install a plugin that you maybe know
from the bounty blog, if you watched it carefully,
the Monster Insights plugin for Google Analytics.
It's one of the most popular plugins out there.
And the way this plugin works is a bit different.
When you interact with it,
there are no requests to the endpoint
like before with the rest route.
There are only requests to admin.ajax.php
and there's the action parameter
which is actually crucial here
because the other way I observed plugins defining routes
was using the add action function.
And the way it works is a bit similar to the rest route.
First, there's the action name,
which is actually the parameter that we can see here,
the action, and then there's the callback function
that will serve a particular request.
And one difference between the register rest route
and this that you should immediately see
that first there is no method here,
but it's not as big of a problem,
but there's also no defined way for the permission check
in the register rest route.
We saw the particular argument,
which was a function to verify permissions.
In this case, there's nothing like this.
So in every single controller,
the code should verify
if the current user has capabilities
or has permissions to make a particular action.
If you are in security for a longer time,
you know that if developers have to do something
over and over and over again like this in the if statement,
eventually they will forget about it.
So there are definitely loads
of access control bugs with this.
And apart from this, there's PHP code,
which processes the response.
And unfortunately, I can't tell you
how to start hacking WordPress plugins.
I can tell you how to define routes,
but eventually what you need
is you need to be able to read this code,
analyze it and find bugs.
So let's come back to the user feedback plugin
and let's actually find a real vulnerability.
One of the ways that I like to search the code
for vulnerabilities is to use a regular expression like this.
It means there's an apostrophe,
which means I am looking for something inside the string.
If the target would be using double quotes,
I would also have double quotes here.
If it would be JavaScript,
I will also probably have backticks here.
Then I'm looking for opening the HTML tag.
Then for anything,
and then I'm looking for the way to insert user data.
So essentially I'm looking for string concatenation
that uses HTML tags,
because then I know that if HTML tags
will be inside concatenated strings,
potentially I can look for XSS.
And in PHP, they use %s
to define the variable inside the string.
So that's why I just have the percentage
because sometimes it's not S, it's something else.
But in general, it does work.
There are a few results.
And I want to look at this one in particular,
because I know it leads somewhere.
It has the A element with the href attribute
that uses the mail to protocol,
which means when you click on the link like this,
the application to send an email is being opened.
And we can see that this syntax,
I'm not really sure what this one means,
but it does mean user data
because they use the sprint function
and they put the row value there.
So let's review what's the row value, what happens here.
And the function is called getQuestionAnswerHTML.
And it just takes the question as the parameter.
And we can see that the row value
is just the value of the question.
And if we take a look at the request we sent earlier
to this endpoint when submitting the response,
it looked like this.
We had our answers, we had the question ID,
and we had the value where the string that I put in.
So now we can see that the row value
that we are interested in this potentially,
the culprit of this vulnerability is just the response.
But we also see the if statement here
that the question type must be an email.
So now let's get to the backend,
let's get to the form that we are,
or the survey that we are using.
So we have the email capture,
the name of the question, I'll just name it the email.
And then we can save it.
To make changes, please duplicate the server,
create a new one, we can create a new one,
we don't, we'll duplicate this survey
because there we already have some responses.
And now we can use the email capture field
and the email name to create a new survey.
We don't really care about many of these,
but we want this to be published, save and publish, nice.
And then we have to open our page
and change the shortcode to two.
Then we update it.
And when we open the other website,
we can see that it allows us to input the email here.
Now, when we come back to Burp and find this response
and send it to intruder, to repeater,
we can see the value of our response.
Let's now just try to inject an arbitrary email
followed by escaping the attribute
and injecting another one.
And we send it, we wait for a little bit
because it sends an email.
In the meantime, when you, in the cut,
I also configured the email client
because this code is actually triggering
in the email generation.
You can see we are in the emails director
in the user feedback email response notification class
because this bug only shows in the email.
It's unexploitable as far as I know.
That's the only reason why I'm showing you this.
I cannot show you a real bug.
And we can see that the email was sent.
I have my environment to see the emails here.
And if we take a look at the HTML source,
it loads for a little bit,
but we can see that we did inject a new attribute into here.
Now in emails, usually email clients
do something to prevent this.
Here as well, here's a CSP on this website
that I use for testing emails
that prevents me from, prevents this alert
from actually popping up.
And the same goes for WordPress plugins
that I used to test these things here.
If we see the response, it's sanitized.
So the alert, so here it's like we didn't have
the injection of the attribute,
but before sanitization we had.
So this is, this bug as far as I know,
has no impact because it's only injecting attributes
into the email and email are untrusted by default.
But if you can find the email plugin for WordPress
that allows you to see the emails that you are sending
and does not sanitize them properly,
feel free to use the part,
the half of the bug that I've shown you
to basically exploit this and get the bounty.
And that's it, it's as simple as this.
So now what's left to be done for you
is to actually go and hack WordPress yourself.
Remember that by hacking on this program,
you can make money yourself,
but also since WordPress is sponsoring this video,
you also support me.
So if you're interested,
go to bbre.dev slash WF and just start hacking.
They are now running a promotion
and you can get up to $10,000
for vulnerabilities in WordPress plugins.
It's a crazy good opportunity
and I'm definitely going to participate myself.
For now, thank you for watching this video and goodbye.